Okay בוקר טוב Boker tov everyone.
Okay
so today's דף daf is ל"ה Lamed hey Amud Aleph and we
pick up at the bottom of ל"ד עמוד ב Lamed daled amud
bet about eight lines from the bottom ואין מקיפין. ve-ein makifin. Okay
and this is going back to the משנה mishnah so the משנה
mishnah has been talking about things you don't do on יום טוב
Yom tov even relating to food and particularly things that are involved
in making vessels and even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who allows מכשירי
אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh presumably would not allow those. It seems
pretty clear he would not. And again I mentioned the ר"ן Ran
idea similar to the idea that you don't go out and harvest
the wheat in the field because even though it's אוכל נפש ochel
nefesh it's something that's done for long term not in the immediate
sort of home context of making food. So even when it occurs
in a home context like we had the idea in the משנה
mishnah breaking a piece of pottery to use it to heat up
in order to fry a fish on it or something of that
nature but it's sort of like making a vessel. It's at least
a דרבנן De'rabonon problem and that you don't do in the context
of food. So now the משנה mishnah though continues or we're going
to do the second part of the משנה mishnah which is less
clear what the problem is. It says that you don't put two
barrels next to one another and like make a fire between them
and suspend a pot from on top of them to sort of
function as an ad hoc stove. That you're not allowed to do
and it's not exactly clear what the issue there is. So let's
take a look. ואין מקיפין שתי חביות. ve-ein makifin shtei chaviyot. So
the גמרא Gemara says it's again seven lines from the bottom after
the two dots. אמר רב נחמן Amra Rav Nachman ואבני דבי
הכסא v'avnei d'bei hakisei מותר לצדדן ביום טוב. mutar letzad-dedan beyom tov.
So you can take stones for that are set aside for the
use of the bathroom not for the use of wiping yourself which
is also what they would use stones for but for the use
of creating like a little toilet to sit on. And you can
like so if they're not מוקצה muktzah they've been set aside but
you're allowed to go ahead and stack them in order to if
it had fallen down or something in order to recreate that toilet
and to use it on יום טוב. Yom tov. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says איתיבי. eitivi. I'll ask you on this. איתיבי רבא
לרב נחמן. Eitivi Rava leRav Nachman. רבא Rava challenged רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman. ואין מקיפין שתי חביות לשפות עליהן את הקדירה. ve-ein makifin shtei
chaviyot lispot aleihen et hakedirah. You cannot take two barrels to suspend
the pot from it. So it's a similar type of a thing.
You're sort of ad hoc creating some walls and putting something on
top. So in one case it's the pot the other case it's
your tush but okay either way what's the difference? אמר ליה. Amar
lei. So he said to him שאני התם משום דקא עביד אהלא.
shani hatam mishum deka avid ohala. There it's different. You're making an
אוהל. ohel. Presumably what does it mean you're making an אוהל ohel
because an אוהל ohel here sometimes it just means like a permanent
structure but here presumably it means אוהל ohel in the literal sense
that there's a roof to it. So in that case you're constructing
again admittedly ad hoc walls and a roof. You have the two
barrels which are the walls and then the pot which is sort
of the roof. Now to your point that's not the real structure.
The structure to the degree there is one is the barrels. The
pot is temporary. But if you cook something over a long period
of time you know the pot is going to stay there and
it's going to stay with this type of roof type cover to
it for hours. Very different than the bathroom type of a use.
Now but okay so it's still at least דרבנן De'rabonon forbidden. It's
not permanent but presumably it's at least a דרבנן De'rabonon problem. Again
it's quite fascinating because you know we would say as I just
said that number one even in the case of the pot it's
not really a roof. It's not a structure that's sort of meant
to function you know to sort of be like as a piece
of the structure. That's sort of the thing you're putting on the
structure to use. And also it's completely not the
forget the permanence that's always an issue but at least there you
could say דרבנן De'rabonon but it's not there to function as a
type of a structure right? So if you want to focus on
the roof I mean the pot isn't there to serve to protect
the area below it. So we will talk about that in a
minute but for now we are going to it's saying that that's
a problem. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes and then we'll
talk about how this applies להלכה. le'halacha. So it says like this.
אמר רב זוטרא לרב אשי. Amar Rav Zutra leRav Ashi. So the
young רב Rav said to רב אשי Rav Ashi אלא מעתה ela
me'ata if that's true בנה איצטבא ביום טוב דלא עביד אהלא הכי
נמי דשרי? bana ista beyom tov dela avid ohala hachi nami desharei?
So it's sort of objecting in the opposite type direction. What? It's
fine that as long as you don't make a roof? So let's
say somebody goes ahead and builds a platform builds like a an
ottoman on יום טוב. Yom tov. Would you say oh wow there's
no roof to it it's just an ottoman fine no problem. So
who cares whether there's a roof or not? It's still like a
little bit of it's a little toilet who cares if there's a
roof? It should still be a problem. אמר ליה Amar lei said
back to him no התם בניין קבע אסור. hatam binyan keva assur.
You're dealing you're creating a permanent structure. Okay I don't care if
it has a roof or not as a roof. You go ahead
and you lay bricks with mortar and you make a wall that's
a problem. That's a בניין קבע binyan keva with or without a
roof. בניין ארעי לא אסור. binyan arai lo assur. But something like
arranging some stones for a toilet or pot you know barrels for
to serve as a type of an oven that's temporary that's very
ad hoc. And therefore that's not a biblical problem. That's There where
it's not a biblical problem, it's only rabbinic, the גזרו רבנן על
בנין עראי משום בנין קבע. gazru Rabbanan al binyan arai mishum binyan
kava. So first the rabbis said we're not going to let you
make even a temporary thing because it'll lead to a permanent thing,
והכא משום כבודו לא גזרו, vehacha mishum kvodo lo gazru, and here
because of your honor, meaning dignity, not giving you something to use
as a bathroom, they did not make a גזירה, gezeira, לא גזרו
בה רבנן. lo gazru beih Rabbanan. Now that by the way seems
to be a shift because it's moving away from the aspect that
there's no roof and it's saying, you know what, maybe you're right,
maybe even in the case of no roof like the בית הכסא,
beit hakisei, they should have forbidden it, but it's a special dispensation
because sometimes we allow you to move מוקצה muktzah for bathroom purposes.
The other case is stones, stones that are used to wipe yourself,
the גמרא Gemara says if you have to you can use them
for bathroom purposes. It's כבוד הבריות, kvod habriyot, it's דוחה לא תעשה
שבתורה docheh lo ta'aseh shebaTorah which minimally means it's דרבנן. drabbanan. So
here it sounds like it's a special dispensation, it's dropping the roof
aspect of it. But of course you can maintain the roof difference
and you could say sure, permanent structure is a problem without a
roof, but a temporary structure is only an issue with a roof.
And that by the way is generally how the הלכה, halacha, the
halachic approach to these things. So anyway it's interesting that the גמרא
Gemara here makes it sound like a dispensation and drops the issue
of the roof. Okay, so anyway let's keep on going. So it
says, where were we?
Okay, so now that's the difference, it's a special dispensation by the
bathroom and maybe also the difference of whether it has a roof
or not. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב יהודה,
amar Rav Yehuda, so says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, האי מדורתא, hai
medurta, if you are going to make a bonfire,
מלמעלה למטה שרי, milma'ala lemata shari, from above to below is permissible,
מלמטה למעלה אסור, milmata lema'ala assur, from below to above... I think
I said it wrong the first time. From above to below is
permissible, from below to above, I'll tell you, from below to above
is permissible.
So what does that mean? I'm gonna really need a what do
you call it?
Oh you have? Oh my gosh, walk around with a marker? Amazing.
I used to walk around with chalk in my pocket but that
was in the...
Okay, so anyway, so why first of all besides which direction you're
doing it, why is it a problem? I mean יום טוב Yom
Tov you're allowed to use fire. So the problem is again something
like creating a structure. If you ever, anybody ever make a campfire?
Right, you don't just throw sticks, right? You create some type of
a crisscross type of a thing, right? And then you probably put
some kindling in the middle. But anyway you're basically creating walls, right?
Now admittedly again, no roof, but you're creating walls. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying you cannot build walls even in this temporary thing
like, again dropping the issue of the roof and even in a
temporary situation you can't build walls on יום טוב. Yom Tov. But
what we will let you do is that's if you do it
the normal way. We'll let you do it in an abnormal way.
Now again I'm not exactly sure how you would do it, but
somebody would like maybe hold that up and then I don't exactly
know how, because
how they're being somehow
suspended, but you somehow have to figure out how to hold up
a higher level and then move some lower,
some wood below it underneath, but you're right I don't exactly understand
physically how you manage that. וכן, v'chen, similarly
an egg. Now what's the egg? So רש"י Rashi says it means
just putting an egg, like putting the pot on between the barrels,
just putting an egg on like a type of a tripod, but
that's crazy because here the focus seems to be anyway about the
walls and nobody says you can't put the barrel on it, it
says you can't sort of
move the barrels to create that type of a structure. So תוספות
Tosafot says it means just like piling up eggs, making a pile
of eggs. Okay, that you're somehow that's seen as like you're building
something. Because it's I don't know there's some sort of like walls
are emerging. By the way, the other thing that makes this bizarre
is that these aren't even עשרה טפחים. asara tfachim. Right normally if
it's not עשרה טפחים asara tfachim it's not a wall. וכן, v'chen,
so let's keep on finish reading this, it's going to sound like
everything is אסור assur and we'll talk about the tripod in French.
Yeah he does.
וכן פורייא, v'chen puraya, a bed.
Now that already makes a little bit more sense, which is a
bed is like a folding bed. So you take out and you
put out like the frame, you know, like this. So and then
maybe you put the mattress on it. So the question is you
cannot do this from bottom up, like first put out, first we're
going to put out the legs and then we're going to lay
this on it, again even though it's all very temporary, but what
you can do is you can hold the beams above and then
somebody else comes and puts the legs underneath. Okay, וכן חביתא, v'chen
chavita,
and similarly a barrel. Now the barrel here רש"י Rashi says is
like
the case of the of the way תוספות Tosafot explains the egg.
It's just making, making a stack of barrels. Okay, also like creating
a, creating somehow that's also like creating a wall or creating some
type of a structure. Now if you take that at face value,
okay, but you could do it if you started
from the top. So you take that at face value, you can't
like stack סידורים *siddurim*, you know, I mean, what, really? You can't
do this שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*? I mean, how far are we taking
this? It's not there's no roof, it's completely highly temporary, it's not
even 10 טפחים *tefachim* high. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* tries to make
sense of this. So let's take a look at the תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* ל"ב ע"ב *lamed bet amud bet* and you see how he's
what how he defines it which is actually how it becomes defined
להלכה *lehalacha*. So the תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* מלמטה למעלה *mimalta lemala* eight
ten lines from the bottom line starts with the word ויש לומר
*veyesh lomar* תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says ויש לומר דכל הנהו אינן אסורים
אלא ella, היכא דמתקין האוהל והמחיצות אבל אם עשה אוהל בלא מחיצות
שרי *Veyesh lomar dechol hanu einan asurim ela heicha dematkin haohel vehamchitzot
aval im asa ohel belo mchitzot shari*. So the first thing תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* says is like the idea of like putting the egg
on the tripod he says that's not a problem just making the
top without making the walls is not an issue you have to
be making the walls and the top. Okay
and then he goes on to explain but all these cases are
cases where you've actually made the walls but that doesn't solve it.
Okay and then he says top of ל"ג ע"א *lamed gimmel amud
alef* fine so that eliminates some cases but still what you can't
stack books? So he says where were we?
That
was even if there isn't going to be something that is going
to function as a roof you're talking
about wait a minute wait a minute
hold on wait just a
second oh yeah sorry I started too late in the תוספות *Tosafot*.
Go to the very beginning of תוספות *Tosafot* back to ל"ב ע"ב
*lamed bet amud bet*. He says like this מלמעלה למטה אסור משום
דהוי דרך בנין binyan, וכן הוי טעמא דכולהו *Mimalah lemata assur mishum
dehavi derech binyan vechen havi tama dechulhu* okay and we already saw
that that's not only when you make the top but when you
make the sides as well because that's the standard case or like
stacking the barrels ואם תאמר היכי מסדרין שולחן שאין לו רגלים על
גבי ספסלין שלו דמתחילה משימין הספסלין ואחר כך משימין עליהם את השולחן
*Veim tomar heichi mesadrin shulchan shein lo raglayim al gabi safsalin shelo
demetchila mashimin hasafsalin veachar kach mashimin aleihem et hashulchan* seems to be
exactly the case the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said you can't do right?
We do it from the bottom up we put little like you
know legs like cylinder like cylinders you know which serve as legs
and then you put a tabletop on it right? So how's that
okay isn't that exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you can't
do and that's from the bottom up and we're making the sides
and we're making the top? So he says ויש לומר דהואיל ואין
להם מחיצות שרי *Veyesh lomar dehoil veein lahem mchitzot shari*. Those are
not walls those are just like legs but they're not really built
up as you know they're like they're not built up as an
entire like plane you know as an entire like so
what not מחיצות *mchitzot*? But of course these things aren't 10 טפחים
*tefachim* high in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* but the point is that
they more operate on a like you know they're more like a
planar than like than just sort of a single leg. He says
וכל הני מיירי דאית להו מחיצות לצדדים המגיעות לארץ *Vechol hani mairi
deit lehu mchitzot letzdadim hamagiot la'aretz*. And all of these are that
they actually have you know wall you know walls that reach that
reach all the way down to the ground and they also go
you know and they also go in a horizontal type of direction.
Okay so basically what תוספות *Tosafot* says is you have to also
be like building the bottom building you know building the walls and
putting the roof on top and that's the issue but again it
doesn't really explain what the issue is in terms of like stacking
books. So even if you said that by the way in these
cases of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* there was a אהל ohel. *ohel*
that was somewhat created there was a gap underneath so if you
make books in a straight stack you're okay but does that really
mean that I can't like stack books at a little bit staggered
so there can't be like a little bit of a you know
a little space underneath one of the books? So להלכה *lehalacha* and
exactly how it fits you know there are I mean this is
like a real issue about how to define this in a way
that makes sense. These are some of the criteria that definitely get
set that A: only if you're building the walls and B: only
if there's a roof on top and C: only if the space
under the roof is like a טפח *tefach* although doesn't have to
be like 10 טפחים *tefachim*. But again the question is at what
stage is it so impermanent and so much not about being an
אהל ohel, *ohel* that it's really not not an issue and it's
a hard גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to understand how to apply that reasonably
in terms of הלכה halacha, למעשה *halacha lema'aseh*. Certainly one factor that
comes in that's an issue that tends to sort of make most
of these cases not a problem but the thing is that it
doesn't seem to be the case in גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is when
as I mentioned the space underneath the roof that you're putting on
top is not made to serve the space underneath. So like you
make a table the tabletop although it creates an אהל ohel, *ohel*
underneath is made to serve the space above not the space below
so it's not really functioning as an אהל ohel? *ohel*. Okay but
the problem is that what? Yeah the problem is that all the
cases in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right now that we just read
are exactly that scenario and nevertheless the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* feels that
under some circumstances even if you have all the criteria you're not
just putting on the top you're doing the walls and the top
you know it's we're talking about a whole like plane it's not
just a single stick but nevertheless I mean okay so you're telling
me I can't like stack my books you know if there's going
to be a gap underneath them. So so they want them limit
it well it's got to be like a... On all four sides.
So if you just put two books and a book on top,
that's only on two sides of a wall. So אין הכי נמי
if you were to have four sides of books and you would
put one book on top and there'd be a gap underneath, that
would be a problem. Okay, so there is an attempt to try
to limit this and limit this, but at some stage this is
forbidding something that does not seem at all to really be about
making an אהל. ohel. But the attempt to limit it is: only
with four walls, and only if you're building both the walls and
the top, and only if it's a plane and not a—not like
a—not a line, but more of a plane. And, you know, and
those are some of the limitations, the criteria that are put on
this. Yes.
Does he explain that this is
actually—you're actually building a type of אהל, ohel or is he saying
that it looks like an אהל, ohel? or you might attempt to
build an אהל? ohel.
Yeah, I mean, it says clearly that it's a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, it's
an עראי. arai. Whether it's a גזירה, gezeira, it doesn't sound like
it. It sounds like, you know, there are things that the—the way
the רמב"ם Rambam puts it in הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos, he says
יש דברים שאסרו חכמים משום שהם דומים למלאכה ויש שאסרו חכמים משום
שהם, yeish devarim she'asru chachamim mishum sheheim domim limlacha veyeish asru chachamim
mishum shehein, I forget the exact language, מביאים לידי מלאכה. mevi'im liydei
mlacha. You know, there's those things that are like, oh, if you
do this, it'll come to this—it doesn't seem like this is going
to come to me building a wall. But, you know, there's some
things that are just in the sort of penumbra of the מלאכות,
melachos, you know, that are similar to it. But look, we wouldn't
say this is similar either, right? All the reasons: doesn't have a
function, not made to function that way, completely temporary, etc. So it's
very hard to understand. And as I said, in הלכה, halacha we
try to define as many criteria as possible that would explain these
cases but also limit their more broader application. But okay, so let's
now continue. The גמרא Gemara says like this. What's a פורייא? purya?
A bed.
Okay, yes, רש"י Rashi seems—is it
like a folding—is it that it comes—yes, okay.
But again, now תוספות would say that we're talking about the fact
that the legs of the bed are not just legs, that they
would actually be like sides of the bed. Right.
Or these applications to these types of beds when you travel. Yeah,
okay.
Also, things that are on hinges is very different. Things that are
on hinges is not like you're doing anything, so that should also
be mentioned. I mean, all these issues around עשיית אהל, asiyas ohel,
okay. But but anyway, but you know, things that are on hinges
even if it's made for an אהל. So again, the attempt is
to limit all of these cases to cases where you've got—you're building
the walls, there are four walls, there's also a roof, there's also
a top, you know, there's a gap between, you know, the top
is is over an actual, you know, sort of space, cavity below,
etc., etc. But even with all those criteria, it's still a little
strange. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues: ואין סומכין את הקדירה בבקעת. ve'ein somchin es hakedira
bevika. You cannot support a pot, let's say wherever it is on
your normal oven, you know, that's tipping over, you can't take like
a stick and use it to support the pot.
וכן בדלת, vechein bedelet, and similarly with a door. So it sounds
like you can't use a door to support your pot. So the
גמרא Gemara says: בדלת סלקא דעתך? bedelet salka datach? Use a door
to support your pot? Really? אלא אימא וכן הדלת. ella eima vechein
hadelet. Similarly about the door. You can't use a stick to prop
up a door. Now, what's the problem? I mean, so let's take
a look. This is going to get into a principle—this—that that line
is going back to the משנה, Mishna, ואין סומכין את הקדירה. ve'ein
somchin es hakedira. So this is going to be that the explanation
of these issues in the משנה Mishna of using sticks and probably
related to the next משנה Mishna as well is this principle the
גמרא Gemara is going to
call—say—which is לא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה. lo nitnu eitzim ella lehassaka.
An idea, question if we פוסקים poskim this way, we'll talk about
that in a minute, but an idea that wood is only for
burning on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it can't be used for
any other purpose. Okay, now so here you have a pile of
of sticks that it's not מוקצה, muktzah, you set it aside for
burning, okay, and nevertheless the rabbis tell me you can't use it
as a back scratcher, you can't use it to support your pot,
you can only use it for the fire. Now it's not exactly
clear what the reason of that is. Like, is that really a
מוקצה muktzah idea, something like מוקצה לאדם, muktzah l'adam, like if it's
set aside for human use it can't be used for dogs, and
maybe since naturally sticks are so much unless they're explicitly—maybe even explicitly—designated
before יום טוב, Yom Tov, but so much there about, you know,
firewood and burning and so on that then, you know, no other
use is seen as like legitimate. Normally we don't say that, right?
Normally once something isn't מוקצה, muktzah, you can have the full range
of use for it. But maybe somehow sticks are always seen as
like fully set over to that. It doesn't exactly—it's not exactly clear
why that would be. So רש"י Rashi suggests another idea which is
later, on—let me just read it inside again to remind myself that
it's more like a rabbinic restriction because of where it might go.
One minute.
He
says עצים הואיל ודרכן לדבר האסור כגון מעשה כלים לא התירו לטלטלן
אלא להסקה. eitzim ho'il vedarkan ledavar ha'assur kegon ma'aseh keilim lo hetiru
letaltelan ella lehassaka.
Like it's like a new גזירה. gezeira. The rabbis are afraid—it's sort
of like a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור—the kli shemelachto l'issur rabbis are afraid
that wood is so easy to use in other types of forbidden
contexts such as a good raw material or something that they only—
It's not מוקצה muktzah. *muktzah*, it's a new restriction. The rabbis only
want to let you use wood for firewood on יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*. Okay, so anyway, it's not exactly clear whether this
idea is a מוקצה muktzah *muktzah* idea or a new restriction, but
that's the way the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* understands what's going on in
the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*. We'll talk in a minute about whether we
rule that way. Let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan:
*tanu rabanan*, אין סומכין את הקדרה בבקעת וכן בדלת *ein somchin es
hakdeira bevika vechein b'deles*, you can't support the wall or a pot
with a stick, לצי *l'tzi*, and here's what the ברייתא baraita, *Braisah*
says: שלא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה *shelo nisnu eitzim ela l’hasaka*, wood
is only been given for burning, meaning it cannot be used for
other purposes on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. רבי שמעון מתיר
Rabbi Shimon matir. *Rebbi Shimon matir*, Rebbi Shimon allows it. Okay, so
he doesn't believe in this principle. Now again, remember Rebbi Shimon is
the one who keeps on coming up in our מסכת *maseches* who
לית ליה מוקצה muktzah, *leis lei muktzah*, which suggests that maybe this
first idea is not a גזירה *gezeira* like רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says
later but some type of a application of מוקצה muktzah *muktzah* that
wood
is considered מוקצה muktzah *muktzah* for everything else. Okay, so that's one
issue, do you have this limited use of wood? ואין מנהיגין את
הבהמה במקל ביום טוב *v'ein manhigin es habeheimah b'makeil b'Yom Tov*, you
also cannot lead your animal with a stick on יום טוב Yom
Tov, *Yom Tov*, like you know, like the shepherds or whatever, they
go with a stick and they, you know, move along the sheep
or they hit the animals every now and then to get them
to move. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon*, Rebbi Elazar
son of Rebbi Shimon, so the son of the Rebbi Shimon we
quoted a second ago, מתיר mattir. *matir*, allows you to use a
stick. Says גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לימא רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון כרביה
סבירא ליה *leima Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon k'avuh sivira lei*, maybe he's
like his father? Meaning it sounds like this idea of using a
stick to lead the animals is the exact same issue: can you
use wood for any other purpose? So it's just the normal debate
about do you hold of מוקצה muktzah *muktzah* or not hold of
מוקצה muktzah. *muktzah*? So the animal thing is just a normal application
of his father's principle. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, דלית ליה מוקצה
muktzah, *d'leis lei muktzah*, and here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explicitly says
the issue of using wood for other purposes is a מוקצה Muktzah
*muktzah* issue. Again, not like the רש״י Rashi *Rashi* I quoted to
you that said it was a גזירה *gezeira*. So anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, so isn't this just an application of that issue
of using sticks for other purposes and a מוקצה Muktzah *muktzah* question?
Says, לא *lo*, no, not necessarily. Here there might be a special
problem. דהא *d'ha*, in this case of the stick to lead animals,
אפילו רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מודי *afilu Rebbi Shimon modei*, even Rebbi
Shimon might say that you can't use the stick to lead animals.
Why not? משום דמיחזי כמאן דאזיל לחינגא *mishum d'meichzei k'man d'azil l'chinga*.
It looks like you're going to the marketplace. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says
חינגא *chinga* literally means like a circle or a cycle, but
like you like cycle around
a fairground, you know, you'll be moving around in a cycle. So
that word is used to describe like a fairgrounds or a market
gathering. So רש״י *Rashi*, so this becomes an issue of עובדין דחול
ovdin d'chol. *uvdin d'chol*, right? If you're going around, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, you know, let's say you have your animal, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* in שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* talks about your cow going around with
a cowbell on it. Okay? So it looks like they're going to
the marketplace. You know, that is an inappropriate at the experiential level
for somebody to be leading their sheep, you know, and leading their
animal with a stick, you know, what are you doing with your
animal? Looks like you're taking it like you're—who is it? Who was
the guy with the—whatever, anyway. I was thinking about the fairy tale,
but the guy who's leading—anyway, it doesn't matter. Okay, you know, but
you're going and you're taking Old Bessie to the market because you're
going to sell her or whatever you're going to do and that's
what it looks like. So that you're not allowed to do, that
is a special problem. It's not the specific problem of the stick.
By the way, it's interesting to note that some—because you know, though—after
a minute ago about the issue about is it an issue of
where it will lead—some פוסקים *poskim* want to understand that there's like
a מראית עין *maris ayin*. You know, oh, it's מראית עין *maris
ayin*, people will think that you're violating שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. They'll think
you're going to the market. That's really not פשט *pshat* of what
this is. This is more issues that we've seen before. Appearances don't
only make a problem because they send you a message that I'm
doing something wrong, the מראית עין *maris ayin* concern. Specifically, especially when
you're talking about שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov*, the way things are experienced has a big impact on the,
you know, texture of the day. And it gets to the whole
עובדין דחול ovdin d'chol *uvdin d'chol* aspect. So even if nobody suspects
me, it feels more like a weekday with people walking around with
their animals leading them by their sticks. Okay, so that's a separate
issue. And that you could say is forbidden just on its own
terms. But the bigger issue here, which is tied into the מוקצה
Muktzah *muktzah*, is: can you use sticks for anything other than firewood?
So let's continue. חזרא *Chazra*. Now, what you're dealing with this חזרא
*chazra* which רש״י *Rashi* says is that this is like a type
of a thing—a stick that falls from a tree, but it's—but it's
got a very sharp—but it's got a very like sharp point. Okay?
And you can use it as a spit, like maybe even naturally
it can be used as a spit because it's got a sharp
point.
Is it just bamboo?
Bamboo. Oh, that makes sense. Okay. So although can bamboo really—is it
sturdy? Could it support? I guess so. Before it cracks. Right. It's
only once it cracks it's a problem. But yeah.
Is it—is it bamboo in בבל *Bavel*?
I don't know. Okay, anyway. חזרא *Chazra*.
Yes, according to Steinsaltz, yeah. Okay.
רב Rav נחמן אסר *Rav Nachman assar*, Rav Nachman says that you
cannot use it as a spit, okay, because again, firewood wouldn't be
a problem. רב Rav, ששת שרי *Rav Sheshes shari*, and רב ששת
*Rav Sheshes* allows it. ברטיבא *B'retiva*, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* qualifies
this debate. ברטיבא *B'retiva*, if it's moist, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור
*kulei alma lo pligi d'assur*, nobody disagrees that it's forbidden because— And
then it's not in a state that could be used as firewood,
so that's considered like completely מוקצה Muktzah because it would have no,
it would start יום טוב Yom Tov without any clear use, although
it can be repurposed like for this. כי פליגי, Ki pligi, what's
the debate? ביבשתא, Be-yavishta, it's dry, so in theory it could be
used for firewood. מאן דאסר, Man de-asar, the one who forbids it,
says לא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה, lo nitnu etzim ela le-hasaka, it
could only be used for firewood, this isn't firewood. ומאן דשרי, U-man
de-shari, the one who allows it, אמר לך amar lach would tell
you מה לי לצלות בו מה לי לצלות בגחלתו, ma li litzlot
bo ma li litzlot be-gechalato, what difference does it make to roast
on it with it as opposed to roast with its, you know,
its embers, with its charcoal? So if you can use it for
the fire, you can use it for the other part of the
fire, for the spit. If you can use it for the firewood,
you can use it for the spit. Okay, which is again pretty
funny because if this idea of לא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה lo
nitnu etzim ela le-hasaka means somehow that that's their defined use is
fuel, you know, what difference it does make a difference whether you're
using it for the fuel or whether you're using it for the
thing that's on top of the fire.
But anyway, again, not exactly clear what this principle is about, but
here he says this is within the, in the, you know, in
the הסקה hasaka category and therefore it's okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri,
some say ביבשתא כולי עלמא לא פליגי דשרי, be-yavishta kuleh alma lo
pligi de-shari, that actually everybody agrees it's permissible if it's already dry.
כי פליגי, Ki pligi, they debate ברטיבותא, be-rativuta, if it's moist. מאן
דאסר, Man de-asar, דלא חזו להסקה, de-lo chazu le-hasaka, the one
who says it's forbidden says when it was dry and you could
use it for firewood, you could use it for a spit, but
when it's moist and it's not fit for even firewood, it's completely
off limits. ומאן דשרי, U-man de-shari, אמר לך amar lach tells you
הכא חזי להסקה גדולה, hacha chazi le-hasaka gedola, no, in theory it
still could be used. If you've got a good strong fire going,
you can throw in even moist wood and eventually it'll catch fire
and burn. So therefore since it's still in the theoretical הסקה hasaka
category, it can be used even in, it can be used for,
for this to serve as a spit. Okay, so here we have
that issue of not using that except for firewood or maybe for
something that's somewhat similar to it, and the גמרא Gemara somehow tying
it into this debate of whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, whether you hold of מוקצה. Muktzah. Again, why this
would be מוקצה Muktzah is not so clear if it has other
potential use. Now again, maybe these cases are that you didn't designate
it from beforehand.
You know, maybe if you did designate it, it would be different,
but without designating then the only way, you know, normally we say
sticks and stones are מוקצה, Muktzah. right? I can't on שבת Shabbos
pick up a rock and use it as a doorstop and use
it as a paperweight. I could designate it beforehand and then I'm
okay.
So here, you know, maybe the idea is that these are sticks
you didn't like designate.
Then we say okay even if you didn't designate on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, normal sticks in your yard, like we'll see the next
משנה, Mishna. even if you didn't designate on יום טוב, Yom Tov
normal sticks in your yard aren't מוקצה Muktzah because you're going to
need them for firewood, but they are, but they still are off
limits for other things. Okay, so maybe that's one way of understanding
this, that we're talking about things that haven't been designated and therefore
their acceptable use, being that they're basically sticks that fell off of
a tree and not things that are like vessels and so on,
is much more limited. But it's an interest, it's not clear why
if you did designate them, you know, to be to use, why
you should have a limited use. Let's take a look as the
גמרא Gemara continues. והלכתא, Ve-hilchata, the הלכה halacha says, the גמרא Gemara.
is יבשתא שרי, yavishta shari, the dry ones are okay even to
use as a spit, רטיבותא אסור, rativuta asur, the moist ones are
forbidden, okay, because they're not usable for any, you know, under reasonable
circumstances for any purpose. Okay, now that might, that's not clear
about whether it holds of this principle of לא ניתנו עצים אלא
להסקה, lo nitnu etzim ela le-hasaka, right? Because if you use the
dry ones, maybe you can use it for anything, but the wet
ones you can't use because those are fundamentally not usable. דרש רבא,
Darash Rava, but we'll get back to the הלכה halacha? in a
second. רבא Rava expounded,
אשה לא תיכנס לדיר העצים ליטול מהן אוד, isha lo tikanes le-dir
ha-etzim litol me-hen ud, a woman cannot go in to the, and
here we're having things that are designated because we're not just talking
about random sticks, we're talking about your, your woodshed, that the דיר
העצים dir ha-etzim is. A woman cannot go into a woodshed to
take a stick to use it as a poker. ואוד שנשבר אסור
להסיקו ביום טוב, ve-ud she-nishbar asur le-hasiko be-Yom Tov, and also if
a poker breaks you cannot use it as firewood. Why? So the
second one is a principle we saw before about vessels that break,
that it's a type of like a נולד nolad because it started
יום טוב Yom Tov reusable as a vessel and now it's only
usable as firewood and that's considered מוקצה Muktzah, for that purpose. לפי
שמסיקין בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים, le-fi she-masikin be-kelim ve-ein masikin be-shivrei
kelim, you can use as fuel full vessels,
but not in broken vessels, and there because that's a type of
like a מוקצה Muktzah or it's completely being re, you know, it's
not the use that it was was set aside for when יום
טוב Yom Tov, began. Okay, so that is the principle of the
broken one. למימרא, Le-meimra, does this mean, the גמרא Gemara says, this
says, דרבא כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה, de-Rava ke-Rabbi Yehuda sevira leh, רבא
Rava holds like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאית ליה מוקצה, de-it leh
muktzah, who holds of מוקצה. Muktzah ואמר ליה רבא לשמעיה, ve-amar leh
Rava le-shameih, didn't
רבא Rava tell to his attendant, טוי לי בר אווזא ושדי מיא
לשינורא, tavi li bar avza u-shadi maya la-shunra, roast for me a
duck and, or goose, and, and throw its innards, the, to, to
the cat. And presumably those innards would have spoiled or are not
normally set aside for human consumption, and the גמרא Gemara assumes that
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda they should be considered מוקצה, Muktzah
you know, the sort of entrails and whatever. So גמרא Gemara says
no,
התם. hatam.
דמסטרחי מאצמיה דעתיה עילויה d'mistarchi meatzma daitei alavih there, since they naturally
spoil, so the same way the goose is not מוקצה Muktzah because
you plan on slaughtering it and eating it, the entrails are not
מוקצה Muktzah because you know that they'll spoil and even so you're
already thinking about the fact that even if and when they spoil,
you're going to feed it to your cat. Okay, so therefore even
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would not have a מוקצה muktzah problem there,
there you plan on it. So what do you have? On the
one hand he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and you can't
use the broken vessels even though they're usable as firewood, they started
שבת Shabbat as a full vessel. Presumably, says רש"י, Rashi, that's also
why the woman can't go in and use the stick from your
woodshed as a poker,
because לא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה. lo nitnu etzim ela l'hasaka. And
that is tied in somehow to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that's a
type of an that's somehow some greater aspect of מוקצה muktzah? that
even wood, as we're seeing in the woodshed that's been designated, somehow
even though it's designated and it's you're going to use it, nevertheless
according to a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda approach, and for whatever reason
wood by itself we won't let you use for anything else. So
now the question comes. So the גמרא Gemara says הלכתא. hilchata. So
is that really the הלכה? halacha. So רש"י Rashi says even though
the גמרא Gemara. fascinating point says הלכתא, hilchata, it's not the הלכה.
halacha. Because the גמרא's Gemara הלכתא hilchata is following רב who we
see holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who holds that he who
does hold of מוקצה. muktzah. We פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon who holds of a much narrower category of מוקצה muktzah and
therefore we hold against the הלכתא hilchata says רש"י, Rashi, which is
quite fascinating. Take a look at רש"י Rashi five lines before the
lines get wide. רש"י Rashi says והלכתא v'hilchata וכולי. v'chulei. רש"י Rashi
says הא הלכתא אליבא דמאן דאית ליה מוקצה איתמרא. ha hilchata aliba
d'man d'it lei muktzah itmara. This whole discussion about whether you can
use firewood for this purpose or that purpose is all according to
the assumption of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who holds of מוקצה. muktzah
אבל אנן כרבי שמעון סבירא לן. aval anan k'Rabbi Shimon sevira lan.
We hold like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בין במוקצה בין בדבר שאינו
מתכוון bein b'muktzah bein b'davar she'eino mitkavein וכרבי יהודה במכשירי אוכל נפש
v'k'Rabbi Yehuda b'machshirei ochel nefesh וכולו שרי. v'chulo shari. It's all permissible.
Okay, so this isn't a problem, this all now of course even
though we knew we know we also do hold of מוקצה muktzah?
but it's a much narrower scope of מוקצה, muktzah it's a רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon מוקצה muktzah and therefore רש"י Rashi says this whole
thing in this גמרא Gemara is totally allowed. Now תוספות tries to
make it work even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, but רש"י
Rashi says that this all is going to be allowed. Now the
amazing thing is not only does רש"י Rashi say that this idea
of using wood for other purposes is allowed, but רש"י Rashi actually
goes back and addresses our case of building the like using the
barrels to build the stove. And I want to read you that
one line because he also says again three lines before the lines
get wide וכרבי יהודה במכשירי אוכל נפש. v'k'Rabbi Yehuda b'machshirei ochel nefesh.
So what's the implications of this? וכולו שרי. v'chulo shari. Now everything
is allowed. בין חזרא, bein hazra, whether the case of using that
bamboo as a spit, because that's about what you use wood for,
that's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda idea, okay? בין סמיכת קדירה bein
smichat kdera ועקבות חביות, v'akvot chaviyot, and also the whole thing about
the barrels and the pots, okay? ומדורת דבי קדירה umdurat devei kdera
and all those things that we mentioned about the eggs and all
that stuff. וכל האמוראים דאסרי אלו לעילא, v'chol ha'amora'im d'asrei elu l'eila,
תלמידי דרב הוו, talmidei d'Rav havu, that's all according to רב, ורב
סבירא ליה כרבי יהודה במוקצה v'Rav sevira leh k'Rabbi Yehuda b'muktzah ואנן
קיימא לן כרבי שמעון. v'anan kayma lan k'Rabbi Shimon. Okay, so we
don't hold of any of that. So what does that have to
do with the issue about making the walls, right, and about the
קדירה, kdera, what's going on there? Right, what do you mean? That's
not about the מוקצה muktzah? issue. So for רש"י, Rashi, yes, it's
not about the מוקצה issue but you know what issue it does
tie into? מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, רש"י Rashi seems to
be saying. And therefore since this stuff is food related, why should
it be a problem? It's just מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh,
it's stuff that ultimately even if it's a few steps removed is
related to food. So רש"י Rashi seems to sort of wipe off
those earlier גמרות. Gemarot. תוספות is not happy with that because as
I've said, anyway, most ראשונים Rishonim assume that things that are related
to like כלים kelim and structure and בנין, even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would say is a problem for מכשירי אוכל נפש.
machshirei ochel nefesh. Including things that we noted because of
עובדין דחול. ovdin d'chol What? Even things that look like עובדין דחול
ovdin d'chol, if it's connected to the preparation of food רש"י Rashi
seems to say like how.
Well, no, no, no. The גמרא clearly had עובדין דחול uvdin de-chol.
as an issue for everyone. But the issues before weren't עובדין דחול,
they were issues about creating an אהל and the different types of
things and רש"י Rashi says, but if they're food related, who cares
that you're creating an אהל? Certainly a temporary אהל. But again, that's
not the הלכה. Okay? But it's interesting we have a הלכתא, hilchata,
we have a whole גמרא that says פסקן פסקן פסקן פסקן pasken
pasken pasken pasken and רש"י Rashi wipes it all off with one
stroke. Yeah, but that's following רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so the מוקצה
issues aren't a problem. We hold like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon so
the מוקצה issues aren't a problem. We hold like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda of מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, so the barrel issues
aren't a problem, it's all okay. All right, that's not how we
פסקן. pasken. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says I'm
sorry, that's what they did in France, the years
I don't know. They didn't necessarily follow רש"י, Rashi, תוספות doesn't agree
with it. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר נוטל אדם קיסם משלפניו לחצות בו
שיניו. Rabbi Eliezer omer notel adam kisam mishlifanav lachatzot bo shinav.
You can take a twig like a little a little splinter of
wood from something in front of you to use it for a
toothpick. Okay, why he says something in front of you we'll talk
about, it's somewhat tied into. It somewhat ties into the next point
about what types, again, what types of wood is מוקצה and what
wood can be used for. ומגבב מן החצר, umagavev min he-chatzer, you
can gather wood from the yard, ומדליק, umadlik, and you can use
it as firewood. שכל מה שבחצר מוכן הוא, she-kol mah she-ba-chatzer mochan
hu, anything in your yard is מוכן, muchan, meaning, okay, this is
the quest besides what can you use the wood for is the
question of what type of wood is considered to not be מוקצה?
Before we discussed a wood shed, I've been talking about designating and
putting things aside, comes רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says even if you didn't designate the wood, if you've got
twigs, twigs lying in your yard and it's יום טוב, Yom Tov?
of course you're going to use them for firewood and you don't
have to designate them and they're naturally usable for that. And you
so they're automatically not מוקצה. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim
say, מגבב משל לפניו ומדליק. megavev mishel le-fanav u-madlik. No, you can't
gather them from the yard. If you've got the wood in front
of you, meaning presumably in the house, then you can use it.
Okay, but not from in the yard. Okay, so presumably that's the
debate of do you what you need to get wood out of
the מוקצה category. So for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer anything in the
yard is not a מוקצה problem. Of course you're going to use
it for firewood. The חכמים Chachamim needs you to have it gathered
in the house. The other issue of whether you can use it
for a toothpick might be the question about לא ניתנו עצים אלא
להסקה. lo nitnu etzim ela le-hasakah. That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allows
you to use a piece of wood for a toothpick, so he
allows you to use wood for other things. When- and the rabbis
might disagree and say no you can use- you can't use wood
for other things. Or תוספות says maybe the reason the rabbis disagree
is if you use it for a toothpick, you'll come to actually
break it and fashion it and carve it as a toothpick and
that would be a problem and that's something the גמרא will get
into. Okay, so two issues: number one, when is the wood not
מוקצה? And number two is: can you use a piece of wood
as a toothpick might be an issue of לא ניתנו עצים אלא
להסקה, lo nitnu etzim ela le-hasakah, might be an issue of a
concern that you'll come to make a כלי. keli. You'll make- you'll
fashion it into a toothpick. Okay, remainder of the משנה. Mishnah. אין
מוציאין את האור לא מן העצים ולא מן האבנים ולא מן העפר
ולא מן הרעפים ולא מן המים. ein motzi-in et ha-or lo min
ha-etzim ve-lo min ha-avanim ve-lo min he-afar ve-lo min ha-re-afim ve-lo min
ha-mayim. Okay, perhaps one of the most important limitations on use of
sort of what the things we can do on יום טוב Yom
Tov is we cannot make new fire. Right, you can't strike a
match. You can't like use your electric whatever you know your thing
on your stove top and so on. You have to keep the
יארצייט yahrzeit thing so you can transfer fire. Where does all that
come out? It comes out from this משנה. Mishnah You cannot bring
fire out, meaning make new fire, neither from wood like rubbing wood
or striking stones or from dirt, which רש״י says basically means like
digging into the ground. I don't know how you'd be allowed to
dig on יום טוב Yom Tov. anyway, and you get some like
you know
hot- apparently sometimes you can dig, I don't know, there's stuff for
you know closer I guess to the molten core or something, I
don't know how far you'd have to dig which is very, very
hot and could make light something on fire. And not from רעפים
re-afim which are like-
tiles that have absorbed heat and maybe then you put a piece
of paper to it or a piece of straw. ולא מן המים
ve-lo min ha-mayim רש״י says is using like water in a cup
as a magnifying glass.
ואין מלבנין את הרעפים לצלות בהן. ve-ein melabnin et ha-re-afim litzlot bahen.
And not only that, you also can't literally whiten, but you can't
heat up a tile to use it then to roast something on
a heated tile. Now why that's not allowed is very unclear. What
should be the problem? That's just part of the process of cooking.
So we'll see that. But the end of the משנה Mishnah: is
extremely relevant for us, but first let's finish with this issue about
the wood. So אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, says רב יהודה:
Rav Yehudah: אוכלי בהמה
אין בהם משום תיקון כלי. ochlei behemah ein bahem mishum tikkun keli.
Food- stuff that's used for animal food, animal fodder, is not a
problem of making a vessel. Right, like we just talked about a
toothpick. You know- so you have- you ever see those pictures, like
the Tom Sawyer pictures where he's got like this piece of straw
sticking out of his mouth, right, between his teeth? So if I
took a piece of straw and I broke it off and I
wanted to use it as a toothpick, did I just make a
vessel? Okay, so he says look, if you use something that's basically
animal food, it's not a vessel. Presumably the reason is is that
A, it's temporary. But not just temporary, meaning if I broke a
twig and used it, we're going to see that that is a
problem. A twig is also temporary. Okay, but it's not just temporary,
it's A, because it's an extreme degree of temporary. You know, it's
something that's- that will be like immediately- consumable or destroyed. But I
would even reframe it. The גמרא seems very much focused on the
fact that it's used for animal food. So the very fact that
it's like defined in some other terms and this is a completely
ad hoc and temporary use means that we're not really going to
look at this as a vessel. Okay, so איתיביה רב כהנא לרב
יהודה. eitiveih Rav Kahana le-Rav Yehudah. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked
רב יהודה: Rav Yehudah: מטלטלין עצי בשמים להריח בהן. metaltelin atzei besamim
le-hariach bahen.
You can- move- it's not מוקצה to use- fragrant wood. You know,
wood that- what would be a good example of this? About wood
that actually has a good smell to it.
Cedar? Cedar's wood bark is fragrant.
Okay. All right. So cedar wood. Cedar's- very fragrant. Okay, so you
can- you can- it's not מוקצה if you want to use it
to smell on יום טוב, Yom Tov, ולהניף בהן לחולה, u-le-hanif bahen
le-choleh, and to wave it in front of a sick person like
as an air freshener, ומוללו ומריח בו, u-molelo u-meriach bo,
and you can like rub it between your fingers because that'll help
bring some of the, you know, I guess scent to the surface,
the- right, and use- and to smell it. That's not a problem.
ולא יקטמנו להריח בו. ve-lo yiktemenu le-hariach bo. But don't break it,
snap it so that you get a fresh part to smell. ואם
קטמו. ve-im ketamo. But ואסור לחצוץ בו
שיניו v'asur lachatzotz bo shinav and but you cannot also use it
as a toothpick, the
where wait a minute, ואסור לחצוץ בו שיניו v'asur lachatzotz bo shinav
לא יקטמנו lo yiktamenu
and there don't break it to make it a toothpick, ואם קטמו
חייב חטאת ve'im kitmo chayav chatat
and if you broke it then you actually biblically have
made a vessel, you've made a vessel. So if you broke it
to smell, that's not a בדיעבד bedi'avad not a I mean, that's
not a biblical problem because you didn't fashion it as a vessel,
but if you broke it to serve as a toothpick, you made
a vessel and you biblically violated. So he says look, here we've
got a problem and presumably this includes animal food, you know, things
that grow that would be used for animal food, and it says
that it's completely forbidden. So אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said
back to him, השתא פטור אבל אסור קשיא לי. hashta pattur aval
assur kashya li. He says look, you know, if you look at
the surface of this ברייתא, baraita you've already got a question to
me when it said that you can't break it to smell, even
if it's only a rabbinic problem because I said it's totally permissible,
it's not a problem at all. So the first part of the
ברייתא baraita is already difficult to me. חייב חטאת מיבעיא? chayav chatat
mibaya?
And if and then it says that not only is it rabbinically
forbidden, it says that you could sometimes you would biblically violate, and
I said it was permissible. So he says on the surface you're
right, how can I have said such an absurd thing? The ברייתא
baraita, says that it's a biblical violation. So obviously there's some other
explanation. It's not like I wasn't aware about this ברייתא, baraita but
it's so extremely against me that it can't really be talking about
the same thing, is what he said. אלא, so here's the explanation.
כי תניא ההיא, ki tanya hahi, when is that saying that you
could biblically violate by snapping a piece of wood? בקשין, bekashin, that
it's hard wood and it's not something that is animal food. I'm
talking about soft, pliable types of straw and so on. That is
even rabbinically permissible. This is talking about hard sticks. So the גמרא
says no, one minute. בקשין בני מלילה נינהו? bekashin benei melila ninhu?
If it's a hard stick, that's not the type of thing you
rub between your fingers to get out the smell. That's usually something
that would be more soft and pliable. So the גמרא says חסורי
מחסרא והכי קתני, chisurei mechsera vehachi katani, it's missing some words, here's
how you have to read it. מוללו ומריח בו, mollo u'meriach bo,
you're allowed to rub it and smell it. קוטמו ומריח בו, kotmo
u'meriach bo, and you're even allowed to break it and smell it.
במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when is that true? ברכים, berakkim,
if it's soft. אבל בקשין, aval bekashin, if it's hard, לא יקטמנו
lo yiktamenu then you cannot break it, ואם קטמו פטור אבל אסור,
ve'im kitmo pattur aval assur, and if you broke it then you're
exempt, period. ואסור לחצוץ בו שיניו v'asur lachatzotz bo shinav to use
it for a toothpick, לא יקטמנו lo yiktamenu don't break it, ואם
קטמו חייב חטאת ve'im kitmo chayav chatat and if you broke it
then you've biblically violated. So basically what has he said? My case
I'm talking about something that's used for animal food and soft, and
that's totally permissible even to break it to use as a toothpick.
The ברייתא baraita that says that it's forbidden, when the first part
talks about rubbing it, that's soft because that's the scenario. But when
it basically says it's rabbinically or biblically forbidden by breaking it, that's
talking about something that's hard that is more not so impermanent. Okay,
and that's when it would actually be a rabbinic or a biblical
violation. All right, so the גמרא says like this. תני חדא, tani
chada, we have one ברייתא baraita that says קוטמו ומריח בו, kotmo
u'meriach bo, you can break it and smell from it. ותני אידך,
vetani idach, another ברייתא Braisa, says לא יקטמנו להריח בו lo yiktamenu
le'ariach bo that you're not allowed to. So now we already can
predict what the difference will be. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב חסדא,
amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav Chisda, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. הא ברכים הא בקשין, ha berakkim ha bekashin, soft or hard.
Now there is a little bit of a difference here, because now
the גמרא is saying that by soft at least it's rabbinically forbidden.
And before we said that by soft, at least by animal food,
it was totally permissible. Okay, so there does seem to be this
issue of what are we saying by soft? Are we saying that
it's totally permissible or we saying that it is that it at
least remains, you know... oh no, I'm sorry, I misstated it. I
don't know where my head is. Let's read it again, because this
also says it's permissible. תני חדא קוטמו ומריח בו, tani chada kotmo
u'meriach bo, one says it's totally permissible. ותני אידך לא יקטמנו להריח
בו vetani idach lo yiktamenu le'ariach bo that you cannot do it.
So אמר רבי זירא אמר רב חסדא, amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Chisda, לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא ברכים הא בקשין. ha berakkim ha
bekashin. When it's soft, it's totally permissible. It is like we said,
I'm sorry. When it's soft, it's totally permissible as we said. When
it's hard, that's when it's not permissible, that's when it's rabbinically forbidden.
I'm sorry, at this stage it is consistent with what we've been
saying. Okay. מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב: matkiv la Rav Acha
bar Yaakov: בקשין אמאי לא? bekashin amai lo? So רב אחא בר
יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov said: בקשין bekashin what's the problem with
hard? מאי שנא, mai shna, you're saying it's rabbinically forbidden even if
it's just done to smell because if it's done for a different
purpose, it'd be making a vessel. Why would that be that we
would necessarily just not allow that since done in another way it's
forbidden? I'll give you a case where we don't make such a
safeguard. מאי שנא מהא דתנן, mai shna me'ha detnan, how's it different
from the following משנה: mishnah שובר אדם את החבית לאכול הימנה גרוגרות,
shover adam et hachavit le'echol mimena grogerot,
a person can break a we've discussed before, like ripping open your
bags of... bag of potato chips to get the potato chips, so
you can break open a barrel to get out the pressed figs,
ובלבד שלא יתכוין לעשות כלי, ubilvad shelo yiskayven la'asos klee, as long
as you're not trying to make a nice opening in the barrel.
Right? This is the whole issue. That's probably the most relevant משנה
mishnah. for our contemporary cases of opening packages, right? So you can
tear open the potato bag from the middle and have it all
splay up, but can you open it from the top and use
it for something that you'll be using it over the course of
a few hours? You know, or is that making it into a
vessel? Okay, so exactly what constitutes a nice way of opening the
barrel that makes it a vessel that's forbidden is the big debate
about packages. But what the point that's being made here is, is
that look, we allow you to do it one way to get
to the food, and if you did it another way, you would
have made a vessel and it would have been, you would have
violated rabbinically, maybe even biblically. So how come there we nevertheless allow
it if you're going for the food and you're not doing it
in the wrong way? And here, breaking a hard stick, we're going
to say is rabbinically forbidden? What's the difference? One minute, so let's
see what he says.
ועוד, ve'od, so that's one question, why there is it rabbinically allowed
when it's not done to make a vessel and here it's rabbinically
forbidden. ועוד, ve'od, and in addition, הני בני רב אדא ורבין בר
רב אדא, Hani bnei Rav Adda veravin bar Rav Adda, דאמרי תרווייהו,
de'amri tarvayhu, the two sons of Rav Adda, they both said, כי
הוינן בי רב יהודה, ki havynan be Rav Yehuda, when we were
in the house of Rav Yehuda, הוה מפשח ויהיב לן אלתא אלתא,
hava mepashach veyahiv lan alta alta, he would like gather up and
give us these beams of, you know, these sticks. Presumably they were
like some type of a cedar stick, which we would break and
smell. אף על גב דחזי לכשישא דנרגי וחציני, af al gav dechazi
lechishasha denargi vechatzini,
even though it can be used for a to something, you know,
if we were to break it, it could be used as a
handle for like a hatchet or a handle for like a spade.
Nevertheless, we broke it and we weren't intending to make a vessel
out of it. We snapped it in order to smell it. So
here's another example of breaking, and this of breaking something hard, that
is going to be permissible as long as it's done to smell,
not to make a vessel. Okay? So you got the question. Until
now we've been saying if it's soft, it's totally permissible. Okay? That's
the point about animal food isn't a problem. If it's hard, broken
to smell is rabbinically a problem, broken to make a vessel is
biblical. And here we're saying, look, here we're allowing it לכתחילה lechatchila
to break into smell. And why is it? And also like the
case of breaking into the barrel to get the food, it should
be allowed לכתחילה lechatchila as long as you're not making it a
vessel. So let's see what the answer is. The גמרא says לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא רבי אליעזר הא רבנן, ha
Rabi Eliezer ha Rabbanan, it's tied to a debate of Rabbi Eliezer
and the Rabbanan. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa and
we're tying it back to our משנה. Mishna רבי אליעזר אומר נוטל
אדם קיסם משלפניו לחצץ בו שיניו, Rabi Eliezer omer notel adam kisam
meshelifanav lachatzetz bo shinav, you can use a little twig of wood
for a toothpick. וחכמים אומרים לא יטול אלא מאבוס שבבהמה. vechachamim omrim
lo yitol ela me'avus shebevehemah. No, you cannot use a piece of
wood. You can only use something from like a, you know, wood
is for burning like we said. לא ניתנו עצים אלא להסקה. lo
nitnu etzim ela lehasakah. You can only use straw for your toothpick,
not wood. So that's one debate about whether you can use wood
for anything other than burning. Okay? But now, ושוין שלא יקטמנו. veshavin
shelo yiktamenu. Everybody agrees that you're not allowed to take the piece
of wood even if Rabbi Eliezer says you can use it for
a toothpick, that's if it's already in that shape. But everybody agrees
that you cannot snap it. ואם קטמו, ve'im kitmo, and if you
did snap it לחצץ בו שיניו lachatzetz bo shinav to use as
a toothpick, ולהפתח בו את הדלת ulehipasach bo es hadeles or to
use as like a door pick, a lock pick, בשוגג בשבת חייב
חטאת, beshogeg beShabbos chayav chatas, on Shabbos you bring a sin offering.
במזיד ביום טוב סופג את הארבעים, bemezid beyom tov sofeg es ha'arbaim,
and if you did it intentionally on Yom Tov you would get
forty lashes. דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabi Eliezer. Now why did they
give the שוגג shogeg example on שבת Shabbat and the מזיד mezid
example on יום טוב? Yom Tov? And the answer is because nobody
wants to say what's going to happen to you if you do
it on שבת Shabbat במזיד, bemezid, which would be that we would
execute you. Okay? Also, it's not interesting to talk about what happens
if you do it on יום טוב בשוגג Yom Tov beshogeg because
you only bring a חטאת chatas when the consequence במזיד bemezid is
כרת או מיתה. kares o misah. So on יום טוב Yom Tov
if you did it בשוגג, beshogeg, there would be no בית דין,
Beis Din, you know, punishment consequence. So therefore we talk about the
שוגג shogeg case as שבת Shabbat, and the מזיד mezid case as
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Anyway, here we have that if you break
the piece of wood in order to use as a toothpick, it's
a biblical violation. Okay? That's what Rabbi Eliezer says.
וחכמים אומרים אחד זה ואחד זה אינו אלא משום שבות. vechachamim omrim
echad ze ve'echad ze eino ela mishum shevus. No, even if you
broke the piece of wood, this is not a real vessel, it's
not a real let's say craftsman way of breaking it, you know,
and this is not really, it's not really a biblical violation, it's
only rabbinic. So now we're saying, ah, now we can explain the
issues now that we see there's a debate as to if this
type of a thing will it really be a biblical violation. So
the גמרא says like this. רבי אליעזר דאמר התם חייב חטאת, Rabi
Eliezer de'amar hasam chayav chatas, Rabbi Eliezer says breaking wood to make
a toothpick could be a biblical, would be a biblical violation. So
he would say הכא פטור אבל אסור, hacha patur aval assur, he'd
be the one that would say don't break the stick to smell
from it because if you broke it in a different way, it
would be a biblical violation. So he would be the one that
would say it would be rabbinically forbidden to break it to smell
from it, and that's like we said before the ברייתא we said
at the beginning. רבנן דאמרי התם פטור אבל אסור, Rabbanan de'amri hasam
patur aval assur, but the rabbis that say that these types of
things, breaking a barrel, you know, breaking a stick, even if it's
made as a vessel So it's not a real making of a
vessel and it's only rabbinic, so הכא מותר לכתחילה. hacha mutar l'chatchila.
So if you did it for a different purpose, then they would
actually allow it. So now we solved the problem, right? How is
it that some sources indicate you're allowed to break something hard and
we're not concerned it'll make a vessel? The source about breaking the
barrel, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that broke the the pieces of cedar
whatever to get people to smell to and so on, because he
would assume that even if you did it intentionally to make a
vessel, it would not be a biblical violation and therefore he's going
to allow you to do it for a different purpose, to break
the barrel to get into the food. Whereas if you hold that
you're not allowed even rabbinically to do it for a different purpose,
that would be because were you to do it for the purpose
of making a vessel, it would be a biblical violation. So it
makes a lot of sense how we line up these various sources.
By the way, it leaves us with a fascinating question. When we
deal with all those issues of opening packaging on שבת Shabbat? and
יום טוב, Yom Tov. are we dealing with a potential biblical violation
or is it only rabbinic, right? And you know, and another thing
to of course consider is that it's one thing to make it
in like a hard piece of wood. Like if you get a
hard piece of wood as a toothpick, maybe it's a reusable toothpick.
If you get a barrel which you made a nice opening into
it, it could be a very much a permanent and reusable vessel.
Okay, but in our case, we're dealing with often disposables. So that's
actually going to be the next two lines of the גמרא. Let's
take a look.
ולית ליה
לרבי
אליעזר הא דתנן שובר אדם את החבית לאכול הימנה גרוגרות ובלבד שלא
יתכוין לעשות כלי. v'leit lei l'Rabbi Eliezer ha d'tenan shover adam et
hachavit le'echol heimena grogrot uvilvad shelo yitkaven la'asot kli. So the גמרא
says, one minute, you're telling me that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who
says that this could be to biblical violations and he would be
the one that doesn't allow you to break the stick to smell
it, so he would rabbinically not allow you to do it for
a different, even in a different way and for a different purpose.
So what does he do with the משנה Mishna about breaking into
the barrel? Would he disagree with that, that you can't break into
the barrel? Now I don't know why you can't say yeah, he's
a תנא, Tanna, but the גמרא doesn't want to assume that. Presumably
he agrees that you can't, that you're allowed to break into the
barrel. Why would he do that if he thinks that there's a
potential biblical violation? So אמר רב אשי כי תניא היא במוסתקי. amar
Rav Ashi ki tanya hi bemostaki. No, he would allow the breaking
into the barrel but it's talking about a special type of a
barrel. It's talking about מוסתקי. mostaki. מוסתקי, mostaki, רש"י Rashi explains, is
basically a barrel that's been patched together from like scrap wood and
is very like temporary, it's not permanent. And basically there even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would agree that it's not really a vessel even
when you make it, it's not a biblical violation, so he would
let you break into it. So רב משה Rav Moshe says, guess
what, says רב משה. Rav Moshe. Pretty much all of our packaging
nowadays is the מוסתקי mostaki category. So even if you held like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that there were that some of these things
could be biblical violations, when you're dealing with disposable types of things,
this last line says everybody holds it's rabbinic, which means it's still
there's still ways that you will do it that it's forbidden rabbinically
to intentionally make a vessel. But when you're doing it for other
purposes, to get into the package, right, and to or to break
the wood to smell, then it would be it would be allowed.
Okay, so we have a debate whether break-make-pack, you know, making some,
you know, very like you know like a very informal way, a
very un-expertise expert way of making a vessel like snapping a piece
of wood for a toothpick or breaking a hole in a barrel,
would that be considered עשיית כלי asiyat kli biblically, or is it
only a rabbinic problem? Certainly if it's disposable and temporary, it's only
rabbinic. And then that leads to the question of are you allowed
to do it for another purpose and in another way, and if
it's only rabbinic, then the answer is yes. And that's opening up
packaging if it's not making it into a vessel, which is always
the question, but getting into the packaging of disposable packaging not being
a problem. Yeah, first Dov then Avrum.
Why is שבת Shabbat? rolled into this as if it were יום
טוב? Why isn't this only and exclusively a יום טוב discussion?
Because צורך אוכל נפש tzorech ochel nefesh doesn't have the same weight
on שבת Shabbat as a היתר hetter as a מתיר.
Well, so you're not, well first no no no, first of all
some of the cases here was the toothpick which is not the
אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. And the case where it was מותר muttar
for the food was the breaking into the barrel.
That's what I'm talking about.
Yeah, but okay, but there it's מותר, muttar, so I don't understand.
It's מותר muttar on שבת, so it's certainly מותר muttar on יום
טוב.
Yeah, but no, but my question I guess I'm I guess I'm
going back to like befo-why should it be why should it be
מותר muttar on שבת? Why should it-we don't have צורך? tzorech?
Well what do you mean? We said we said that even if
you did even, oh, why is it מותר muttar at all on
שבת? Well okay, so that's a good question. So first of all
if the what the גמרא is saying is even if you made
it into a vessel it would only be rabbinic, and you are
not even and you're basically not even making it into a vessel,
you're you're just destroying it. So but besides it קלקול, kilkul, right,
it is קלקול kilkul and you could say okay it's like it's
but but you don't have to say קלקול, kilkul, I mean רש"י
Rashi on that משנה in שבת says קלקול. kilkul. But what the
גמרא here is saying is there's no איסור issur to do it,
to break the barrel and make it a vessel would be only
rabbinic. So when you're not making it a vessel and you're just
breaking into it and destroying it together, there's no איסור. issur. Why
should there be an איסור, issur, right? So side the opposite way,
what's the problem here? There's
no
d... Well no, if it's just opening it the normal way and
you're not creating it a new shape to it.
But a normal way, let's say so, I'm...
No, no, that we had before like some knotted thing that keeps
something down, like a manhole cover. If that's the normal way of
use, that's totally fine. Here we're talking about actually like breaking into
it, you know, and changing its shape, like making a hole in
it. Yeah. Three questions. Three questions, yeah. Let's see if we have
time for all of them. Yeah, we don't. Yeah?
Is this
a—so is this a unanimous—well, unanimous thing because I have the impression
that there are people who are concerned about making a hole in
a cereal package?
Yeah, so I was trying to be clear. If you destroy the
package, almost nobody is concerned. That's the case of most cases. The
question is and where all the debates of packages is, is what
qualifies as not destroying it but as making it into a usable
vessel, right? And that's the whole debate. Does opening the top of
my potato chips in a convenient way, is that making it into
a vessel? No, it was already a vessel, it was already a
vessel beforehand. Anyways, so that's where the debates are. But tearing it
in the middle and destroying it, everybody says it's okay. Okay, fine.
Let's just get to the bottom of the דף. daf. We won't
do the fire, but I do just want to read a few
more lines. תוספתא Tosefta לגבי legabei מן החצר, min hachatzar, you gather
from the from the yard the wood,
so what's—when is the wood not considered מוקצה? It has to be
in your house or even in your
yard. תנו רבנן: מגבב מן החצר ומדליק, Megabev min hachatzar umadlik, שכל
מה שבחצר מוכן הוא. she-kol mah she-be-chatzar muchan hu. Anything in the
yard is considered, you know, implicitly going to be used for firewood.
ובלבד שלא יעשה ציבורין ציבורין, U-vilvad she-lo ya'aseh tziburim tziburim, but just
don't make it into big piles. רש״י says because then it looks
like, you know, you're doing you're doing it for like long term
and again it's a type of an עובדין דחול. רבי שמעון מתיר.
רבי שמעון lets you make it into big piles.
במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamifligi? What are they debating? מר סבר מחזי דקמכניס
למחר וליומא אחרינא. Mar savar mechazi de-kamachnis le-machar u-le-yoma achrina. The one
says that making it into big piles of wood looks like they're
sort of planning for the future, you know, and you're doing this
whole thing to get, you know, for long-term purposes. ומר סבר קדרתו
מוכחת עליו. U-mar savar kederato mochachas alav. And the other one says
no, you got a fire burning there and you got your pot
on the fire, it's clear you're doing it for the sake of
right now and it's not for the sake of long term. I
just will say one word about the fire, you know,
let's—I'm sorry, I know we're up but I want to just say
one thing about the fire before we end. So let's just read
it's like five words in the גמרא. אין מוציאין את האור. Ein
motzi'in es ha-or. You don't make new fire. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
משום דקא מוליד ביום טוב. mishum de-ka molid be-Yom Tov. You're creating
something new on יום טוב. So what does that mean and what
is the parameters? You can't—what is defined as מוליד, molid, what is
something new and so on? I will say though that this is,
you know, there's a ריטב״א Ritva that makes it sound, and some
ראשונים Rishonim that make it sound that it's less about the fact
that it's something new and it's more—or maybe the problem of it
being new has to do with the degree of effort that is
required to make a fire. You know, so you go ahead and
it's like really like a יש מאין, yesh me-ayin, you know, you
gotta rub and rub and rub. I think I mentioned once that
whole scene from Tom Hanks, what was it called, Stranded? Or Castaway.
Castaway. You know, anyway, what it sort of means to make a
fire and to and to and to create it almost like a
יש מאין yesh me-ayin and there's a lot of effort involved as
well in it. So some ראשונים Rishonim point those aspects out. Which
I just want to say is interesting because that's not our reality,
right? Our reality you strike a match, two seconds, no effort and
so on. There still is a יש מאין yesh me-ayin quality to
it, so obviously the הנחה hanacha is that this applies, you know,
completely in our day as well. But it does raise interesting questions
about what are you putting in that category. How about turning on
an electric burner? You know, and it gets like red hot and
so on. Do we call that אש? eish? And if we call
that אש, eish, even if we call that אש, eish, is that
called מוליד molid or, you know, in terms of what the גמרא
is concerned here about מוליד molid is? So this as I said,
what? So the hot tile we'll talk about but the גמרא says
hot tile is a different a different issue. The burner is only
a problem if it's—becomes like red because then it at least might
be in the category of אש. eish. But this becomes like one
of the biggest issues you have to while you're doing there doing
all this cooking and making all these huge fires but striking the
match that's forbidden because that's like a real יש מאין yesh me-ayin
type of a thing. Okay.